Hey guys, welcome back to Mental Health
Monday. So good to see you and have you
here with us today. Uh Dr. White, good
to see you. It's been a few weeks. I
think it's been three.
>> Tell me about it. But uh I'm sure you
enjoyed your Thanksgiving.
>> I did. I did. Oh man, did I ever have
something to be thankful for. I mean, I
always have something to be thankful
for, but this time it was like I got to
my brother got to come and spend
Thanksgiving and uh some of you know he
had a massive stroke last year on
November 15th and then he's doing so
much better that he was able to to come
and it was really um a blessing
>> to have him here. So, it was I was
really really thankful
>> and we ate good food, too. Oh my
goodness. Yeah. Um definitely ate uh
great food. Uh me and my mother held it
down.
>> That's good.
>> Yeah. Thank you. Uh one day I' we've
I've had Florence's food before and that
was amazing. I have to we me and my
husband have to have your mom's food. Is
it Panameanian? What's the main What's
the staple dish from Panama?
>> I would probably say aros compoo. Um
Okay. What is that? Like that's rice and
chicken. Uh
>> okay. Okay.
>> But uh but because a lot of us are of
really Caribbean, you know, origin.
>> So a lot of Caribbeans migrated to
Panama to work on the Panama Canal. So
>> right,
>> we, you know, we identify very much with
Jamaicans, the Yuka, the Dashin, the
>> um Aki Saltfish. I mean, yeah. I mean,
all all of that.
>> This is a fun fact. I used to
many moons ago before I met my husband
obviously dated a panameanian
and his mom cooked so good and it was
really she was cooking Jamaican food but
she cooked the Jamaican food really
really good.
>> Absolutely.
>> That was like Yeah. So I I I I know what
you're saying.
>> Absolutely.
>> I know what you're saying.
>> So that's really good. Well, welcome
back you guys. We're happy to see you
guys. Guys, I hope we hope you guys had
a happy Thanksgiving and a break, but we
are back for a few weeks before we take
another break for the uh Christmas
holidays, but we're excited to be back
with you now. We want to hear from you,
see where you guys are viewing from.
It's always fun to see where you're
viewing from. Um, and just, yeah, tell
us your name and where you're viewing
from.
um so that we can say hi to you and
welcome you here to Mental Health
Monday. So, please let us know. We're
excited um again to hear from you. And
what we're doing this evening, as you
could see, at the last minute, I did a
little Instagram and I don't know how
many of you guys came over from
Instagram, but a little uh video
inviting all of you or whoever um was
was on my Instagram inviting you to
Mental Health Monday and uh definitely
was inviting people on um social media
earlier uh today. So, we're just excited
to have you guys and we are taking your
questions. Um, and we're gonna uh try to
answer them. We are going to try to
answer them. All right. So, we're taking
your questions about relationships,
marriage, family.
It's all inclusive. If you're single,
please put your questions in. We like to
we like to answer our singles questions
as well because you're preparing for
marriage one day, even if it's your
second time.
or even third. I don't know. It's like
we're here to to answer those questions.
Okay, we have a stess afani, I believe.
Um I think that's how you say it. I am
sorry if I said that wrong, but from
Teri, California. I know exactly where
you live because I am from Pastor
Robels, California. And like if you I
know this is in the valley, but if you
I've passed through to Larry many times
and so welcome. It's good to see you
here on Mental Health Money Monday.
Clint, of course. Good to see you.
Always.
>> Clint, you are a real one. You're always
You're always here. It's like if if
we're here, you're here. So, I would I
don't even know how many you've missed
in the last almost four years, like
three and a half years. Probably. We
could count it on one hand. I'm sure. I
am sure. But it's good to see you um
from Long View, Texas. You don't even
have to put in the chat. I know exactly
where you are unless you're somewhere
else. All right, so we have
>> not sure not I don't have a name but
watching from Philadelphia. That is
wonderful. Good old Philly
high school in
>> um well at Pine Forge but Pottstown,
Pennsylvania about 45 minutes out of
Philly.
>> Can you hear me?
>> So um I don't know if you guys hear that
my cat is trying to get in my in this
office room. He's like banging on my
door, but he thinks he's a dog. I think
he's a cat, so he needs to calm down.
[laughter]
>> All right, so welcome again. We're
taking your questions, so please put in
the chat
>> uh your questions on marriage and
relationships. And again, singles, your
questions are more than welcome. Yes.
So, I said your name right, Estes Estes,
Estasani.
>> Microphone check. I'm so thankful that I
said that right. And again, I know
exactly where to.
So, yes. Um, yes, Clint, you do try to
be consistent. You and you have done
that. You have definitely done that.
>> Microphone check 1212.
>> Can you guys hear me?
>> Yeah, I can hear you. I felt like I was
just talking and talking and talking,
but I just thought you weren't. But I
could hear you all this time.
>> But I was saying stuff. I was asking
you, do you know where Tary is? Oh, I
never heard you say I can hear you now.
I honestly I thought you weren't talking
and I'm so sorry. I did not hear
[clears throat] you before.
>> I'm just like [laughter]
my my my husband and my kids will be
like, "Yeah, you do that all the time.
You're always talking talking talking."
[laughter]
>> Sometimes they'll be like
>> sometimes my and my kids are not kids.
The youngest is 20. They're very much so
grown adults, like grown grown and and
they'll they'll say in and the I am the
odd one in our family like when they're
driving in a car they just want to
listen to music
>> like just and just meditate and just
look at the road and and I'm just like
let's talk and they're like mom could
you like we just want to chill like we
don't want to talk and um yeah and then
if if I don't have anybody to talk to in
the car then I'll just call somebody. I
do most of my calling like when I'm
driving in the car.
>> Yeah, I've gotten a few of those calls.
>> So, I guess I'm the weirdo. I guess the
majority of you guys like to just be
quiet and I don't want to be quiet in
the car.
>> No, I I think it's a mix. I I definitely
love the sound system and how like music
sounds in the car. So, I definitely love
>> you have a good sound system. I mean, I
do too, but I don't use
>> So, I love that. But I do enjoy a great
conversation. It is so nice to have an
awesome companion with you. Um, and a
drive is just a wonderful time, I think,
to communicate. So, I don't think you're
strange in that sense. [laughter]
>> Even if I was the only one, I wouldn't
care. But, all right, we [laughter] have
a question.
>> Oh, yeah. What do we got?
>> Oh, go ahead. You can read it. I've been
doing a lot of talking. You read it.
>> God says, "Test him by returning tithes
and offering faithfully, and he'll pour
out from the windows of heaven and
blesses." What if after years of doing
this, you are not impressed with the
results? [laughter]
>> Oh my god,
>> that [laughter] was enough. I think I
think you guys should save that for the
Sabbath school um for the Sabbath school
question.
>> I think so. I think so. I was like, so
yeah, send that. Please send that to um
to the question and answer email for
Living Man Church so we can put that in
the in the pile of questions. And I
think Pastor Myers would would answer
that one. Um,
>> I'm sorry about that, Enoch, but that
definitely gave me a good chuckle for
this Monday, which I greatly
appreciated. He said, "I'm not too
impressed with the results." I love
that. Um,
>> please do not trivial, please. No
trivial illustrations like this material
thing or that. What I've desired from
God as blessings has been centered on
relationships with people and the
necessary things to live with dignity.
what I've desired from God as blessings
has been centered on relationships with
people and the necessary things to live
with dignity. And he issued a warning.
He said, "Please, no trivial
illustrations like this material thing
or that." Okay, beautiful.
>> Well, now he brought it over into the
relationship realm. And so he did.
>> Well, then let's talk about that.
>> Okay, I'm gonna let you take the stab.
>> I think relationships are a really
interesting thing.
Because it's in relationships where
sometimes the thing that you are seeking
is the very thing you need to give,
>> is the very thing you need to create.
And knowing Enoch, he looks like
somebody who has given, he sounds like
somebody who's given and given and given
and given a lot. And so it might very
well be that it's not being
reciprocated.
um which I honestly don't have a good
solution for.
>> Um that said though, um I I find that in
relationships,
I mean, we've all heard that it's better
to give than to receive. And the
illustration I have in this is one of
the coolest experiences I've ever had in
life was throwing my wife a birthday
party. A surprise birthday party.
throwing my wife a surprise birthday
party.
>> All of the all of the logistics and the
theorizing and then her friends and and
and her super good friend. Um, shout out
to Cynthia Brisco and but her her super
good friend like the work she had to do
and see how like
stubbornminded my wife [laughter] is,
you know. Um because like she had to,
you know, tell her, "Okay, well, we're
going to book this session over, you
know, to get a massage." And my wife
like went behind her and cancelled the
massage. I mean, like she was
impossible. She was impossible. Like
when they came in to the surprise,
Cynthia was looking at my wife like like
just kind of really crosseyed like you
are a pill. But um but to the the the
the look of joy on Florence's face, the
look of joy,
>> um it stays with me totally.
>> It's it's and and it was me giving.
>> It was me giving.
>> Yes.
>> I I've gotten a lot of cool gifts. And
I'm not gonna I don't know if you can
identify with this, Enoch, but like I I
feel so uncomfortable being given
something like I feel you know you ever
have you ever been made to feel
uncomfortable like being the center of
attention? Tante's like I don't struggle
with that. [laughter]
Like she's like
>> Oh, that's funny. I I don't but
>> No, I don't think you do. [laughter] I
don't think
>> I mean people think my kids think I
don't get nervous. They're like, "Mommy,
don't you get nervous when you have to
get up and speak and do?" I'm like, "No,
I get nervous, but I just take a deep
breath and just
>> and then it just all clicks on." But
anyway, everybody's personality is
different. But yes,
>> absolutely. But there there's a measure
of discomfort, but whatever the case,
that felt wonderful. And what I'm
saying, Enoch, is
is that
we we are all surrounded by people.
And
if we're wanting them to give and that
being a measure of the quality of the
relationship, I think sometimes we'll
have a lot, you know, it'll leave a lot
to be desired. If on the other hand, we
view it as an opportunity to get good at
giving, I think sometimes that can make
it a little easier to build value into
the relationship and to feel good
yourself. Now, that said, no, this is
not a one-way street and giving, giving,
giving, giving. No, it that it just
doesn't work that way. So, that's
definitely not what I'm trying to
champion. Um, but I am saying sometimes
relationships where you get an
opportunity to invest is something
awesome. And I'll I'll finish with this
example, Enoch. Uh,
my wife and I weren't really we we
weren't really excited at the prospect
of having a big family, a family period.
Actually, we were we were very
selfishminded and thinking we're just
going to marry and focus on ourselves,
you [snorts] know.
>> [laughter]
>> But, you know, I think we I think we
just were I mean, us specifically, we
were just like, you know, having kids,
we've seen what it does. We've seen how
it strains relationships, and we were
like, we were not feeling that.
>> Uh, so there [snorts] is nothing I
>> I definitely can I can respect that for
sure.
>> Yeah. There there's there's there's
nothing I've done that is as challenging
as having a child. And it's this
evolving thing because it constantly
requires a different aspect of you.
>> Mhm.
>> And it is unquestionably
the best
thing that we've collaborated on. It is
without question the best collaborative
project, you know, that we It's just
>> like it's it's an amazing experience and
it requires so much of you.
>> Yeah. And it does give up and it does
give to you as well, you know. Uh but
yeah, I think relationships are a
reservoir to give is what I'm saying.
And
>> yes, yes, I would. Absolutely. I hope
that was helpful.
>> Absolutely.
>> I look forward to your feedback.
[clears throat]
>> Yeah. No, that No, no, no. That was that
was a great answer. I think we have
several other questions, so we should
get
>> You could read this one.
>> Yeah. Yeah. You could read this. Um, if
someone has a lot of work to do and
mental health healing,
how long should a person have to focus
on themselves in therapy?
There's there's no um the way I'm
understanding that question, I mean,
there's no
timeline on a healing process and
focusing um on yourself. Um, it's it's
it varies. It's different for every
person. So there's no can't say like
well it should take this amount of time.
There's really no um
time limit that our answer with a time
limit that we could give to answer that
question. That's how I see it. Do you
have a question answer?
>> The the the variables are
the severity of the trauma.
>> Then you have the protective factors.
Mhm.
>> You know, that's another variable.
There's the skill of the therapist.
Then, of course, there is the
therapeutic alliance between the client
and the therapist.
Four variables. Don't you love how big
my hands are? Of four variables. Um, and
each one is on a spectrum. So, all of
those variables would go into account to
determine the speed of healing,
>> right? Um so so that's why it's hard to
say but those are those are just four
factors I identified the qu the skill of
the therapist the quality of the
therapeutic alliance u between the
therapist and the client the severity of
the trauma the protective factors and
the risk factors.
>> Yes.
>> All of those things would go into how
quickly you're going to heal.
>> Yes. All right. In what situation should
a person uh give another the silent
treatment and is it really healthy to do
so?
>> That's absolutely I'm answering the la f
last part of the question. It is not
healthy to do so. It is not healthy at
all. Matter of fact, I tell my clients,
my couples, um
the silent treatment is not allowed.
What is allowed when you're in once
they're in therapy and they're trying to
improve on their marriage? What is
allowed is
you can let them know that I need to
take to step away and take some time and
to think about something and to actually
calm down or cool down whatever the case
may be and set a time to come back and
talk about it. Um but the silent
treatment is not healthy and you're
actually you think you're not
communicating you are absolutely
communicating in silence. um they call
it meta communication because you're
still your body language the silence
you're it's you're telling your spouse
that I don't respect you enough right
now or I don't care about this
relationship right now to actually or
I'm so angry right now or you're saying
a lot of things while you're being
silent and you're not helping uh the
situation for even when you do speak and
so you're actually making it worse. Um,
and so I like to the rule that when I'm
working with couples, the rule that I
that I um like to give them is that
again you have to say you cannot just
walk away and be silent. You have to say
okay and this takes
enormous amount of maturity. Enormous
amount of maturity because you're not
feeling what you're saying. What you
feel like is I just want to be silent.
But that is not the best way to go. You
can be silent. You can take some time,
but you have to communicate that you're
taking some time and set a time to come
back and talk about it at a later time
that day. Um, they don't know a lot of
times that people don't know that I'm
giving them a Bible principle with that.
But when the Bible says, "Don't let the
sun set on your wrath." Do not go to bed
angry
because the anger is just going to
cultivate and do its thing even in your
sleep. and when you wake up, you're not
better. You guys haven't spoken. You
went to bed angry. You're going to have
to have that conversation, but it
doesn't help uh the situation. So, you
have I like to tell my my couples that
they need to talk. They need to speak at
some point before they go to bed. They
need to come to some piece. and maybe
they need to talk about it more the next
day, but they've come to a place where
they can talk and then maybe table it to
the to the next day, but they're not in
that space of anger. I'm not talking to
you. I'm so angry with you. I can't
stand you. None of that. Um, and again,
that takes a lot of maturity, but that's
what you should have when you get
married. But it's not what we have when
we get married. That's why we have so
many problems. Go ahead, Dr. White.
>> Wow. She knew. She knew. Well, you know,
my usual joke to that question is, I
don't think my wife and I would be alive
today if we didn't let the sun set on
some of our um arguments. Uh so, I mean,
so yeah, we will go to bed um we will go
to bed uncomfortable at times from time
to time. Uh I'm sorry, but then you wake
up in the middle of the night and a lot
of times you've forgotten everything and
you're just like, "Hey, why is she so
far over there? get over here. You
[laughter] know,
>> she doesn't want to touch you. That's
why she's mad still.
[laughter]
>> And you forget, you know, but you get a
good night's sleep. You kind of you get
a little distance from the thing. Then
your brain does the amazing work that it
does to to sometimes consolidate the
issues and you're like, "I was wrong on
that one." Yeah, I was wrong on that
one. Or unfortunately, she was really
wrong on that one. No, I'm joking.
>> Yeah. This is probably one of our major
times we'll probably disagree a little
bit because I find like even
physiologically like if I go to bed
angry at my husband.
I the stress I I mean I'm carrying all
that like I don't feel well. I literally
don't like feel well, you know, because
I'm like I'm carrying I took this I
didn't matter of fact I didn't actually
get good get I don't sleep if I go to
sleep angry at my husband I don't get
good sleep. It's not restful sleep. I
maybe it's women versus men. I don't
know if anybody can relate to what I'm
saying. Like maybe men sleep well even
when they're mad at their wife, but
women I for myself I it's I don't sleep
well.
>> I sleep but it's not good sleep. I don't
think I really enter into that rim sleep
that we need.
>> Uh Florence says laugh out loud and Ant
knows what's up.
>> Thank you Florence. Thank you.
[laughter]
>> Um
>> thank you.
>> Okay. I think it's men versus women
then. Well, I still make my clients do
what women do.
>> I not make them, but I encourage them
to.
>> The other piece to the silent piece is
where I say do not say the first one,
two, three, four, five, six or seven,
you know, things. Um it can be it can be
really really helpful
to give some thought um give some
thought to what you want to say so that
what you're saying is actually helpful
because don't ask me why
um but sometimes the things you are
impulsively wanting to say are likely to
make the situation much worse.
>> Yeah. Um, so I I think you know I I
think those that's that's sometimes the
role for silence. Now what you don't
want to do is what Sister Tante is
talking about and that is to weaponize
silence.
>> Like I'm not advocating for weaponizing
silence. You weaponize silence. I'm
going to make you feel the full brunt of
the of my absence. I'm gonna like and
it's and it's done in a spirit of
resentment, you know, and it's like I'm
going to I'm going to make you I'm gonna
be like a wall, you know, like no, there
is weaponizing silence and that's not
what I'm championing. And I think this
is where I agree with the tante that
>> you you really don't want to weaponize
anything in the context of marriage,
including um silence. You don't want to
weaponize sex. You don't want to
weaponize you don't want to weaponize
anything.
>> Um so that's where I agree. I'm just
saying be intentional about your
interaction. And by the way,
[clears throat] I also am not saying I'm
going to bed and you just like going to
bed. Usually we go to bed in surrender.
Like we are exhausted. We've tried every
means to kind of reconcile it and we're
just getting further and further and
further apart. And we have a rule where
we don't want cops coming to our home.
We don't. That's [laughter] not
>> You don't let come into your house.
We're not letting cops come to our
house. Um, that's not happening.
[laughter] We
PD need not worry about the the address
of the White House. You need not worry
about that. No.
>> Yeah.
>> So, so that's where we're like, no, it's
all right to get a little distance um
between the issue so that maybe
sometimes the perspectives can shift,
>> right?
>> So, no. And I I can understand your
perspective now, especially if you're
going to bed in the way that you
described.
That's at least cuz like I cuz I think I
mean I said that too like you may not it
may not be completely resolved but
you're in a better headsp space
you know when the cortisol levels way up
here like you're so angry that you can't
even barely whatever even like stand to
look at each other or whatever. If
you're way up here like that's not going
to be good rest but you need to at least
be right here with some peace and be
like okay we're at least here. Let's we
can continue the conversation tomorrow.
But but kudos to you on you guys. It
sounds like you consistently
don't let the sun set on your That's
That's dope.
>> We try We try not to I mean, it's
literally not good for my health,
literally. So, I'm like, listen, we have
to make peace. We have to make peace
before I go to bed because it's too
much. And I need my sleep. I need my
sleep. Um I think we have another
question. I need good sleep, not just
any sleep. Let's see.
So, I got asked this and didn't know how
to answer. How can I be in heaven with
someone that hurt me?
In this case, sexually, someone who
destroyed a big part of your It says
question mark. Um,
does it let's see does it make sense or
it doesn't make sense. I don't know if
they're trying to say doesn't make
sense. Um, I don't know. Make we want to
make sure we're understanding your
question correctly, but I know I
understand the first part correctly. Um,
how can I be in heaven with someone that
hurt me in this case sexually?
>> Okay. So, um,
on December 19th, 700 p.m. Pacific, um,
I will be doing a presentation on, um,
heaven and pastor Ivor has said that
living mana will be, you know,
supporting it. So, I do look forward to
the uh, to the opportunity for us to
really delve into the topic of heaven.
>> Amen.
>> Uh, what is the illustration I can think
of now?
Um
I first and foremost
if you're asking this question and you
have been harmed by someone I mean I I
offer my sincerest condolences to to the
trauma
>> uh because the very nature of trauma is
it just doesn't make any sense. It just
does not make any sense. It's like
ultimately trauma leaves you asking the
question, why did you do that? Why would
you do that? Just tons and tons of
questions.
Um, in a heavenly context, in a heavenly
context, one of the things that's going
to preede going to heaven is what I call
1,000
years.
1,000 years of IMAX is what I call it.
But Revelations talks about having a
thousand years.
And Sister White talks about one of the
things that'll be done during that
thousand years is the books will be
opened and you will get an opportunity
to have your questions answered.
Um, you get to ask your questions. You
get to explore. You get to see your
story. You get to see some of the story
of others. You get to delve into the
topic of your choosing and really and
truly gain some clarity. And God gives
us a thousand years to answer our
questions.
>> And the idea being and I and I think
part of what that does is it will give
you a context. I think ultimately when
you spend a thousand years understanding
something, I think it opens the door for
your perspective to shift. I'm not I'm
not saying that your perspective will be
nullified or it's but I just mean you
get to understand. A lot of times when
people experience trauma, they're they
want to ask questions. And the the the
prerequisite for going into heaven, like
one of the things that just will precede
heaven is a thousand years of asking
your questions. So you you I can
guarantee this, you will have clarity as
to why people are in that space of
heaven and you'll also have clarity on
why they're not.
>> Right. Absolutely. So, so, so God is
intimately
intimately interested in making sure we
get our questions answered. And that, my
friends, is just the beginning because
that's not necessarily the end.
>> You're probably going to have questions
that go beyond that millennium. Well,
you now will get an opportunity to
answer it even further throughout the
ceaseless ages of eternity.
>> Right?
There's um um and I'm quoting my my
husband in this story. And if you've um
seen the blueprint or maybe it's a love
story, I don't remember what sermon he
put it in, but uh he shares um like
Stephen will be in heaven and he'll be
in heaven just praising the Lord like
praise him, praise him. Then he'll look
over and he sees Paul and he'll be like
what? because Paul,
you know, murdered him or had him
murdered [snorts]
>> and he's and he's going to be looking
like and it's it's a joke that my
husband says and he's going to be
looking like God, did you did you make a
mistake? Like this is the person who
like like took me out. So
going back to what you shared and
connecting that it's just like God
[clears throat] is going to be able to
answer our questions and because of this
the um the state of mind that we're
going to be in these earthly things and
the hurt that we experience on this
earth, God is going to be able to wipe
away all of the tears, all of the pain,
everything is going to be wiped away.
And I believe that's how we're going to
be able to stand in heaven even with
those who on earth abused us and hurt
us. Um
>> well, but thank you for bringing that up
because we won't even be delving into
those questions with the same mind,
>> right?
>> With the same mind. Like one of the
things that trauma does
>> is it breaks you and it shatters you and
it emotionally scars you. Well,
in the in a moment, in the twinkling of
an eye, we shall all be changed.
>> That's right.
>> We shall all be changed. We will have
new physiques.
>> Yeah. We We're going to have new
physiques. We're going to have new
mental capacities,
>> new minds.
>> Absolutely.
>> So, some of the questions you have now,
>> they they're probably going to change to
some degree. And what I'm I'm not trying
to neutralize the significance of the
trauma,
>> but I'm I'm just trying to acknowledge
some of the biblical realities that
we've been given that tell us we're
going to be dealing with some of these
issues with a completely different mind.
>> Yes.
>> Um
>> that's right. Okay.
>> Let me thank you for the question.
>> Yeah, absolutely. How does a married
couple do effective marriage counseling
if my spouse doesn't believe anything I
say and seems to twist everything I say?
Well, that's quite interesting. But you
guys are doing marriage counseling with
a couple. How does a married Okay, not
you're not being the counselor you're
in. Okay, I get it.
>> I think I misunderstood that at first.
Okay. How does a married couple do
effective marriage counseling if a
spouse doesn't believe anything I say
and seems to twist everything I say?
That's hard. That's difficult. Um, as a
marriage and marriage um and family
therapist,
um,
I'm really processing this. There's some
there's situations where
uh
couples are not really in the space to
have therapy as a couple. There needs to
be individual therapy first for couples
counseling to be effective. And you
know, I'm not telling you what to do,
but if I was if I was your therapist and
I was brought into this situation and
everything that you say or everything he
said, you didn't believe him or they
turned it around or whatever. And if it
if it if it was so extens if it was so
difficult, if it was to a point where we
could not really move forward in the in
dealing with the problems that you came
in for, then I would suggest individual
therapy first or individual therapy at
the same time. And that's not always
very feasible for you know to be paying
for individual therapy and coup's
therapy. So I would sometimes I will say
let let's take a break and let's deal
with let's it get into some individual
therapy and then let's come back and
approach couples therapy.
I I I think that the the complexity of
marriage is simplified tremendously
when we start realizing that a
successful marriage requires skill.
It it requires skill and sometimes I
wouldn't it wouldn't it be helpful if we
stop focusing on trying to heal the
marriage and instead maybe we focus on
building some skill sets.
>> Yeah.
>> Building some of the basic skill sets.
Hey, um how do you listen to a person?
>> Can I can I at least do that?
>> And you have to do it at work. Nine out
of 10 times you've got you've got to
listen to people you can't stand at work
>> and be respectful at work. Exactly.
Absolutely. And what's the payoff? A
paycheck.
Well, well, in marriage, what's the
payoff? A union that protects your kids
and that
>> I love it.
>> That a community is, you know, held
together and supported with. I mean,
that that's a pretty big payoff. Well,
we do it at work. So, like sometimes if
we can just focus on skill sets, how do
I listen to you? How do I communicate in
a way that um you hear me? And this is a
big one. This is just a big one. What do
I do with my frustration?
>> What What What do I do with my
frustration?
>> Because you know what's interesting? If
you squeeze a grape Yeah. If you squeeze
a grape, what do you get? You know,
>> grape juice.
>> Grape juice.
>> You squeeze a grapefruit, you get
grapefruit juice. You squeeze an orange.
Orange juice. And when you squeeze a
fruit, you get its juice. Well, what
happens when you squeeze a human? This
is what makes humans so amazing.
You might get one thing if you squeeze
me in the morning [laughter] and you'll
get something else if you squeeze me in
the evening. You'll get you'll get
you'll get one thing if you It's really
interesting because I really listen to
that analogy. Um, and your your goal
really and truly is how do I how do I
produce the same fruit juice? And and
that really is the work of the Holy
Spirit. How do I produce the same fruit
juice when I'm tired, when I'm angry,
when I'm jealous, when I'm fearful? How
do I create? And that is the work of the
Holy Spirit. But it's a skill set.
>> It's also a skill set. And I think
sometimes an important part of healing
marriages is let's let's get better at
this.
>> Let's get better at this. Because if you
kept damaging your car, you would want
to learn, hey, what do I need to do to
stop damaging my car?
>> Right. Absolutely.
Absolutely.
All right. So um I don't know if we have
another question but but while you guys
are uh just to remind you we are taking
your marriage and relationship questions
even singles we're taking your questions
as you can see and we are trying to uh
do our very best uh not when we see your
questions we don't know your situation
specifically so we are giving you the
best answers um that we can um but
please put in the chat
If you have questions for uh myself or
Dr. White, we would love to uh answer
your questions again about marriage,
relationship, family, single life. We're
here for it.
>> Can I can I promote my little webinar
that
>> I was just going to say? Yes, you
certainly may.
>> Thank you so much. So, we all know the
holiday seasons are super stressful.
[snorts] Um, and in dealing with stress,
there are tools and there are skill sets
for dealing with stress. And so, in our
stress mastery webinar, which is
happening at 700 p.m. Pacific, uh, we're
going to be talking about some of the
key frameworks for dealing with stress
effectively, especially getting you
through the holidays and preparing for
2026. Yes, it's here. And have you
noticed that we are like over booked?
You have like three different events you
could choose from each of the remaining
weekends.
>> And the problem with that is this is
like the last chance to do some very
important reflecting on what worked last
year, what didn't work last year, and
what you want to do going forward in the
future. M
>> so don't let the busyiness
rob from you the opportunity to pause,
reflect, and grow. So join us 700 p.m.
Pacific
>> um Eastern Standard Time um Eastern
Pacific Standard Time. And then Atante I
mean um Amra has put the link for you to
register.
>> Put it in the link.
>> I mean in the chat in the link
[laughter]
>> put the you can see it. Yeah. So, so
yeah, you know,
>> I'm excited to see you guys.
>> No, that's wonderful. So, you guys
definitely check that out.
>> Um,
there's there was a comment that I I
think is is is a comment and it's a
praise the Lord comment. Uh, it says, "I
was in therapy after my div divorce for
three years. I recently let her go. Loc
has helped me to understand God's word.
The Holy Spirit um the Holy Spirit lets
um her know." So that's a blessing. I
think that's a praise the Lord. Glad
that the church has been a blessing to
you.
>> Well, thank you for that, Candy. And
praise God indeed.
>> Yes. And I was going to say, you know,
this I was we were doing question answer
this this last uh Sabbath for Sabbath
school and I was like quoting you so
much. I quoted you twice. I know. I
quoted you uh I talked about your um um
oh my goodness, why am I forgetting your
name? That's burning um killing burnout.
So I mentioned that because I was
answering the question and then I used
some of the the concepts that you use in
that book and then um I was answering a
question and I was talking about
exercising of course the beautiful no
instead of the ugly yes and yeah so I
was just I was like I was giving you
credit. I was saying Dr. White and blah
blah blah blah. So anyway well thank you
for that. Thank you for that.
>> You're welcome because it was definitely
from you. But again guys, we have about
about 13 minutes left and we will answer
your your questions on relationships,
marriage, single life. I mean at this
point if you have another mental health
question, we may be able to tackle that.
Uh but there's just um again 12 minutes
probably now uh left and so if you have
a question that you want to ask me or
Dr. white or if we can both pick take a
stab at it, that would be that'll be
fantastic.
Um, looks like we're getting another
question coming in right now. I think
it's a question. All right, here it is.
Another Okay. Some couples seem to enjoy
doing everything together. Example,
working at the same place, etc., while
others seem to be around each other all
the time.
Um, what makes the difference there?
>> Well, I have to say, yeah, I mean, I can
say that definitely me and my husband
are with each other quite a bit. Um,
because we he works from home. He's a
pastor. However, our church is um, as
you know, is online 100%. So, and our
studio is right here as well. So,
um, he's, you know, he's here and I
work, um, I would say 75% from home and
then the rest of my of my clients are,
um, I go to my office to see them. So,
we see each other a lot. So, a lot of my
clients are online. Um, so we see each
other a lot, but this last week we were
apart for seven days. And I think that
was the first time we spent seven days
apart in like 27 years. I know we've
done like five or four or maybe even
six, but it was like a whole week and we
really missed each other. So, it is so
it is good. [laughter] Like we really
were like I was like you need to come
home now, but you know he had things
that he had to take care of um family
things and so
>> uh but I do think some being apart on
some level is is fine. I mean it's
whatever works for people. I mean, some
people are like, you know, I know other
marriages that they might go every month
they might have to go a couple of weeks
apart. Their marriage is still very
strong. I mean, I just can't, you know,
every I don't that really wouldn't work
for us. I already know. But for some
people, it it does work because of their
jobs. They have to be apart uh a couple
of weeks out of the month. So, and their
marriage is still very strong. So,
>> well, first of all, I think it's really
awesome when you are apart and you
actually miss each other and you're not
like and you're not like
>> we need to do more of this.
>> Yeah, I was I know. I was cuz I was
really sad and I was so happy to be go
to the airport and pick him up. But go
ahead.
>> Yeah. For for So, for me personally, you
know, I got to keep it real with you,
Deborah. Um, first and foremost, I'm
attracted to my spouse. Um, so I enjoy
looking at her.
Uh, and I like her in my proximity. Um,
I enjoy touching my spouse. Um, just
keeping it real with you. And so that
that helps, you know,
>> right?
>> Uh, what's the other thing? Um, I enjoy
our banter.
I like to say whenever when Florence is
in a bad mood, then she's polite to you,
[laughter] right?
So, it's like, well, you're being
polite. What's wrong? [laughter]
>> That is really funny. You guys are
hilarious.
>> But, but when she's in a good mood,
she's ribbing you. She's, you know, she
it's it's it's it's hilarious. Um, but
>> it's like to be together.
>> It's fun. It's It's um It's fun. So, I
think that's that's one factor.
Um I mean and that that's what I would
have to describe in my situation. I mean
yeah
>> so [snorts] somebody
from the other side would have to be a
couple and they could comment on it but
that's that's my comment on it
>> from my perspective.
>> All right. How do you approach a
conflict in marriage um which you and
your spouse are in disagreement about
methods of disciplining teens? Oo mercy
the teen years. Okay. [laughter]
>> Oh,
>> it's hard guys. It is. It can be rough.
It can be rough. Um and you're not in
agreement.
>> This is beyond um
>> TV podcast
>> since Dr. White is being so transparent
tonight, which is usually I'm more
transparent than you, but [laughter]
you're being really transparent. Um,
wow. I mean, it's just like any I'm I'm
not going to just focus on the teen
thing. Okay. So, if I if you were if you
and your husband were um bringing that
into my office space, I would really be
giving you the same answer to any
disagreement. It's it's not it's not the
topic, it's how you disagree, right? Um,
you should be able to
sit down calmly and lay out your your
opinion and why uh you feel that way.
Um, I'm assuming
you're here on a Christian YouTube
channel. So, I'm assuming you could
possibly you guys are are a Christian
couple, so you're going to take the
principles from the Bible. I was going
to use this this last past uh Sabbath to
answer a question. um but about
disciplining because um if you're
Seventh Day Adventist then you know
about Ellen White and you believe um and
that she's a prophet and her in her
council uh she talks about never
disciplining in anger. So you could at
least come to a point where you say
listen
our child is doing something that we do
not want. They do need to be disciplined
for whatever reason. um you have to come
together and figure out what that is.
But however you're going to to
discipline the child, it needs to not be
in anger. So you guys could at least
come to that point in agreement
hopefully. I really don't know the
dynamics if one's a Adventist or one's a
Christian and one's not. Um because
I really don't know the details enough
to be able to give. But I'm just
assuming maybe one wants to use physical
punishment and one doesn't or you know I
don't know I don't know the dynamics.
Maybe you could give us a little bit
more. But um regardless the way you guys
are talking about it together is
you're still coming at the topic just
like any other topic in your marriage.
I've talked about it here. I've talked
about it in answering questions um on
Sabbath uh for during Sabbath school as
well. that, you know, you have to learn
how to communicate with empathy and
understanding, especially with a topic
that you don't agree. So, you're really
trying to hear the heart of the uh of
your spouse to see where they're coming
from. um really hear their their
I don't want to say hurt and pain, but
just their emotion and feelings and why
they're coming at this and this
conclusion on why they want to
discipline the uh the teenager this way
and why they want to and then they need
to listen to you and why you want to
discipline the the teenager in another
way. So, you're not cutting each other
off in your communication. You're not uh
building a defense. You're not you guys
are on the same team. act like you're on
the same team. Your Christians, I would
say definitely pray about how you decide
to discipline a teenager and just do it
with the spirit of God and Jesus and
come at your, you know, come at your
teenager like that. So, I'm kind of
mixed in how you deal with the teenager
and how you guys communicate, but you
come at the problem like you do any
other problem. You have to communicate
with empathy, understanding, and that
takes a lot of maturity, but that's the
way that you have to hear each other to
hear why you're different. You have
differences on how you want to
discipline.
>> Y'all need to cash up on that one. Um,
put put your cash up in the in in the
chat because uh that those are some
bombs. There's a lot of bombs. Listening
to the heart, hearing what's said,
what's not said. But I think but you you
and you separated it into the two issues
that are present. One issue that is
non-negotiable is alignment. Parental
alignment. You can't be divided. Like,
>> right,
>> you can't be divided. How you guys
arrive at that alignment? That's the
million-dollar question.
>> Um, in a lot of Christian homes, they
talk about, well, the man being the
leader of the home, and, you know, I
think you guys collaborate as much as
possible, but then this person might
have the final say. I what what works
for you works for you. But alignment,
you guys have to figure out parental
alignment because when you present to
your kids, when there's not alignment,
they they kind of shred you. They know
how to have you guys play against one
another.
>> Absolutely.
>> Now, to the kids, this brings up this
burning issue about corporal punishment.
>> Corporal punishment. And I would
interview I would introduce my comments
in terms of are you disciplining or are
you punishing?
>> Are you disciplining or are you
punishing? And guys, can we be honest?
>> So many times there's way more punishing
than disciplining.
>> Absolutely.
>> Disciplining is like discipling. You're
trying to win them,
>> right? And and punishing is done in
rage, you know? I'll show you in rage.
And guess what? Guess what? It collapses
when they become teens and especially
later teens because beating and like
physical, you know, physical punishment
to an almost grown adult. I think you
can see how it gets ridiculous really
fast. Really fast.
>> Absolutely. And this is why when they
are young, you know, the verse in
scripture is train up a child. It didn't
say beat up a child. It didn't say it
said train up a child. And here's the
key thing in training.
>> In training, when the person goes wrong,
there is corrective action.
>> There's corrective action. There is, and
what do I mean by corrective action? I
mean, you study the situation and you
see what is it that I need to impose
here that would help this child not make
this mistake again. That takes
creativity. Guess what? That takes
energy. And guess what? You guys as
parents are often short on,
>> energy, time. It's like, and so you do
what comes natural. You do what was done
to you. And you know what you do? You
scale it down one level and say, "See,
this is better than what I got."
>> Yeah. you should see what I'd gotten.
And then we think that it's adequate.
And we also misquote scripture. So we
use scriptures like um um spare not the
rod and spoil the child as if those
shepherds back then were beating on
those sheep. [laughter]
>> Like they were walking around beating
them with the rod. My wife dropped this
sign on so I got to give her credit for
this one. She's like they weren't using
the rod to hit the the shepherds or the
sheep.
>> No, they weren't.
>> They they were guiding them. they were
guiding them. So they're saying don't
don't fail to guide them. If you spare
not the guidance,
>> you will spoil the child. And then so
I'm like, if you really want to try to
justify beating them, a better verse
would be uh foolishness is wound up in
the heart of a child. But the rod of
discipline, yet again, you I I could see
why you might make that mistake, but yet
again, it goes back to the rod of
discipline
>> is discipline. It's discipline. It's not
punishing.
>> It's not punishing. And can I give you
the cherry on top?
>> Can I give you the cherry on top? Here's
the cherry on top.
>> Cash app, too. This you're killing it
right now. [laughter]
>> App
here's the cherry on top. Ladies and
gentlemen, you are raising your parent.
>> Yes,
>> you are raising your parent. Remember,
once a man, twice a child. Yeah,
>> we as adults, we are rapidly getting to
ages where we are more and more
vulnerable.
>> And guess what?
>> That fury and some of those mistakes
that we made to those children with
those children and and and teaching them
how to be physically violent, these are
chickens that may very well come home to
roost for some of us.
>> Yes. You really want to remember you are
raising your child and the discipline
that you extended to them, they may very
well turn around and extend back to you.
And this is why I'm saying
train up a child. Don't beat up a child.
Train up a child.
>> And I'm not advocating for not taking on
the responsibility of training them.
Don't neglect them. don't. No, they they
they do need to be trained cuz my
goodness, I can't stand brats.
>> But
>> that's right.
>> But by the same token, I I also hate
abuse and where it really comes from a
place of rage and we are doing way more
punishing than actual discipline,
>> right?
That like I said, you you you need to
cash out for that one. So I mean that
was great.
>> Totally. No, that no absolutely that was
that was that facts as the young people
say. That was facts. That was truth.
That was beautifully said. Um
very bold. You were very bold. I don't
know if we have any Caribbean uh parents
here, but that was [laughter]
that was very bold. That was very bold.
We have cultures that absolutely just
never
probably ever thought about that
principle that you just shared. I mean,
they just were taking what they thought
and were trained and told that that's
what those scriptures meant and those
that's not what those scriptures mean.
And
>> and first generation beautifully
beautifully said, beautifully done.
Guys,
>> we are all out of time this evening. We
appreciate you stopping in during this
very busy time of the year just to hear
some hopefully get some your questions
answered, get some good tips on how to
deal with your relationship and and um
and your family. But we definitely um
just appreciate you guys stopping by and
we would love to see you here next week.
Please, if you are are here for the very
first time, even if no, not if you're
here for the very first time, you need
to like and subscribe. Everyone needs to
hear good good um answers and to
questions about marriage and
relationships. Um even if you were
single, uh we have past programs that
we've talked about that a lot. So,
please like and subscribe and share with
your friends and let them know what they
missed, but even though they missed it,
they can still see it again on the
replay. And we will see you next week.
Dr. White. It was great doing program
with you and we will again see you guys
next week.
>> Same channel on YouTube, same time. You
guys have a good evening. Bye bye.
>> Take care. Bye bye.